A sharp needle breaks [music] skin and
pierces the firm, dark tumor. Millions
of viruses invade deep into the deadly
cancer, kick-starting an experiment that
[music] had never been attempted before.
Bypassing some of the most sacred safety
nets in medicine.
This is the story of [music] Dr. Beata
Harassy, an expert virologist from
Croatia, who decided to cure her own
cancer.
Thanks to her help, we can tell it as
accurately as possible.
It had been a few years since Beata had
been diagnosed with breast cancer, a
pretty bad one. After a surgery to
remove as much of the cancer as
possible, [music]
she went through four cycles of pretty
harsh chemotherapy. The goal was [music]
to eliminate every last cancer cell that
was still hiding in her body. And the
chemo did its job. All rapidly dividing
cells in Beata's body died en masse. The
cells of her immune system, hair, and
mucosa, [music] and digestive tract died
in droves. We'll spare you the details,
but it wasn't fun.
Beata was sure that if this harsh
treatment would not destroy the cancer
completely, then nothing would.
Unfortunately, at least one cell
survived. After two years, it came back
again and was removed again. And again,
>> [music]
>> it came back stronger, bigger, and now
even more dangerous than before.
A hard, dark mass that had begun
invading Beata's muscles and skin,
getting ready to spread all over her
body. Stage 3B. If it was allowed to
succeed, her chances of survival were
very slim.
This is where Beata decided to take care
of this cancer herself with the support
[music] of her colleagues, because they
actually had a unique mix of expertise
and resources. Her plan was as simple as
it was daring. They would breed viruses
[music] that they were deeply familiar
with from her lab and inject them
directly into her cancer.
Why viruses love cancer.
Like many medical advances, this one was
discovered by accident.
>> [music]
>> In the early 20th century, baffled
doctors observed that the tumors of some
cancer patients shrank when they got
virus infections like influenza or
measles, which makes perfect [music]
sense if we understand how both work.
When regular cells are infected with a
virus, they fight back hard and without
compromise. [music]
First, they slow down calming their
internal machinery so the virus has a
harder time taking them over and making
copies [music] of itself.
Then they scream for the immune system
to send antivirus killers, which usually
means that they'll be [music] killed
themselves. And if they can, they push
their self-destruct button and take the
virus with them.
Cancer cells are unable to use any of
these defenses [music]
exactly because of the corruption that
makes them cancer.
They're unhinged and hyperactive,
[music]
eating and reproducing feverishly,
unable to slow down. Cancer cells also
can't really call the immune system to
help them out because it's trying
[music] really hard to kill them.
Successful cancers actually build a
protective zone around them that hides
them from immune cells [music] or even
kills them. And lastly, their
self-destruct button is broken. [music]
So, viruses are a horrible enemy for
cancer cells slaying them effortlessly.
But much worse, once a virus starts
killing, [music] all of the ensuing
death, virus, and tumor particles
attract the immune system, which then
happily joins the massacre.
Viral therapy became an [music] active
field of research and a big hope for
beating cancer.
Unfortunately, it turned out that using
viruses to kill cancer is way harder
than initially thought. You've got three
very complex [music] players trying to
kill each other fighting inside a living
human being that somehow has to survive.
Cancer is also very much not cooperative
[music] in its own destruction and often
very hard to reach, especially if it's
already spread throughout the body. And
in the end, [music] you need to kill
every last cell to really slay it.
Cancer is also a living, evolving entity
and does not look exactly the same in
[music] two people. So, it's extremely
difficult to find virotherapies that
work in many different patients.
On top of all that, cancer is typically
[music] treated with chemotherapy first,
often with incredible results and great
survival rates.
The author of this video is only alive
because of [music] chemo, so we're not
talking it down at all. But one of its
most brutal side effects is that it can
severely weaken your immune system. And
[music] without your immune system at
its A-game, virotherapy can't work
properly because it's doing most of the
slaughter.
As an expert virologist with extensive
experience, Dr. Hadassah knew all of
this.
So, she developed a plan.
>> [music]
>> She would take her chances, forego
another round of chemo, and keep her
immune system ready to fight.
Beata would engineer her own anti-cancer
virus mix and do her own virotherapy.
Nobody had done [music] anything like
this before.
Even with all of her experience and
resources, this was not going to be
easy.
Viruses might actually be part of the
solution here, but online, we prefer
they stay far ah ah ah
ah ah ah away from us. And
>> [music]
>> NordVPN is our weapon of choice against
them. Go to nordvpn.com/cutskazat
[music] to make sure malicious websites
are blocked, web trackers stopped, and
scam web [music] shops identified.
NordVPN's next-generation antivirus
[music] scans files during downloads,
removes malware, and blocks ads
automatically, and they warn you of scam
calls before you answer.
>> [music]
>> NordVPN also protects you during travel
season by encrypting your connection
when you connect to unknown Wi-Fi
stations in hotels, airports, or cafes.
[music]
You can choose from a thousands of
servers in 224 locations around the
world
>> [music]
>> to access your home content from abroad.
You can also book hotels or rental cars
more cheaply thanks to the price
difference in different countries,
[music] regardless of whether you're
surfing with a computer, tablet, or
smartphone. NordVPN is compatible with
all major platforms and can be [music]
used on 10 devices simultaneously. If
you want to discover all the services
NordVPN offers, go to
nordvpn.com/kurzgesagt [music]
to get 4 months extra on a 2-year plan,
all risk-free with NordVPN's 30-day
risk-free refund [music] guarantee.
Great, that's sorted. Now back to useful
viruses.
Beata's viruses.
In labs, viruses are usually produced by
injecting them into cell cultures,
letting them multiply, and then
purifying the mix,
creating a liquid with mostly viruses,
>> [music]
>> but also some cell debris and garbage.
This is good enough for most lab
experiments, but would never be allowed
to be used in humans.
Anything that goes into [music] our
bodies has to be clinical grade, way
more pure to be as safe as possible.
Beata decided the risk was acceptable
for her. So, her next big question was
which virus to inject.
The main thing she was looking for was a
virus that specifically attacked [music]
the cell types the cancer emerged from.
Ideally, it shouldn't cause a serious
disease because surviving cancer doesn't
help if you then die of Ebola.
And this virus had to have been
clinically tested [music] in humans
before. So, for her first virus, Beata
and her colleagues chose
>> [music]
>> measles. Not the wild, dangerous type
that killed about 100,000 people in
2024,
the weakened and pathetic version we've
been using in the measles vaccines for
over 40 years.
Beata went to work and together with her
team produced her first dose, a syringe
filled with about 600,000 measles
viruses.
The plan was to get an injection every
few days for the next few weeks and
monitor closely what would happen to the
cancer. And so, the experiment began.
The needle was pushed directly into her
cancer, a dark, hard tumor growing and
thriving. At first, nothing [music]
seemed to be happening, but after the
second dose of tens of thousands of
viruses, the tumor suddenly exploded,
[music] almost doubling in size and
became more spiky, aggressive-looking.
After two more injections, [music] the
tumor began to shrink and constrict.
What was happening inside [music]
Beata's body?
Let's go back in time. After the first
injection, the viruses couldn't believe
their luck. They'd found [music] the
most amazing hunting grounds and they
went to work infecting, killing,
multiplying.
Cancer cells were screaming in panic and
dying by the millions. The tumor turned
into [music] a battleground leaking the
broken parts of dead cells and countless
newborn viruses. Until this moment, the
cancer [music] had been protected by a
chemical defense zone around itself,
hiding from the immune system. No
anti-cancer cell could [music] cross it,
but the measles massacre shattered the
protection.
There's nothing that makes your immune
system more aggressive than evidence of
cells being killed.
Death is always an emergency. And with
that much death and virus parts leaking
into healthy tissue, Beata's immune
system suddenly jolted awake in shock.
Not only was there an enormous virus
[music] infection that somehow had been
able to fester, no, there was something
else, a hidden army suddenly ripped from
the shadows and without protection.
Beata's immune system chose violence.
Like angry angels of death, millions of
immune [music] cells invaded the tumor
furiously fighting and killing viruses
and cancer. This sudden influx of cells
is what caused Beata's tumor to swell so
explosively. What followed was an epic
and unhinged massacre. Viruses killed
[music] defenseless cancer cells, virus
hunter cells gobbled up viruses, and
cancer killers exploded cancer cells
left and right, while [music] cancer
cells still fought back and deactivated
immune cells where they could.
Every few days, fresh injections
followed, saturating Beata's cancer with
at least 80 million viruses in total,
keeping the massacre going.
There was one problem, though.
The immune system was too good [music]
at its job. Soon, Beata would be totally
immune against measles and likely
eradicate the virus, which might end the
therapy before it finished.
So, after a few weeks, Beata started
injecting a second virus, VSV, a pretty
harmless relative of rabies that causes
mild flu symptoms in the extremely
[music] rare cases a human catches it.
Within a day after the first VSV
injection, Beata fell ill with a fever
and chills. But amazingly, these would
remain her only side effects during the
entire experiment.
Her immune system was freshly offended
and once again hurled itself into the
tumor with newfound anger.
The massacre continued as unhinged as
before.
After 2 months of injections, the tumor
was only a shadow of its former self.
63% smaller, it had turned soft and lost
its density. And critically, it had
completely [music]
stopped any advances into the muscle and
skin tissue.
Now, surgeons removed the weakened tumor
and examined it in the lab. Half of its
mass was immune cells angrily bashing
cancer cells to death.
Beata had beaten her own cancer.
To be sure no survivors could grow back,
[music] her doctors treated her with
additional anti-cancer drugs for a year.
But at the time of the making of this
video, it's been 6 years and her cancer
has [music] not returned. It seems that
Dr. Hadassah has cured herself for good.
Why don't we treat patients more often
this way?
Beata's decision to inject herself with
viruses earned her much admiration and
applause, but also a ton of criticism
from medical ethicists. Mostly because
the viruses and methods she used were
not approved for use in humans, which
begs the question, why is it so hard for
patients like her to access experimental
treatments? Well, the reality is that
many things in life are not really right
or wrong, but exist on a trade-off
slider. There's no correct decision,
just which payoffs do you want to
accept? [music]
In this case, if you make medical trials
easy, fast, and cheap, then there'll be
experiments that will seriously harm a
few people, but on average you'll make
more progress faster, which will
potentially save [music] more lives in
the end.
If you make medical trials hard, very
slow, and expensive, on average you'll
harm fewer people and can be pretty
confident that the new therapies [music]
are pretty safe,
but you also hugely slow down medical
progress and even completely prevent
some new therapies.
In today's world, the slider is firmly
on this side. So, as a result, many
novel cancer therapies are usually only
given to people who've exhausted all
other conventional therapies and whose
[music] cancer is very advanced.
As a last resort of sorts.
At the time of making this video, over
100 studies are actively [music] testing
viruses against cancer in humans, but
the vast majority are restricted to
late-stage cancers.
And this slows down progress because it
[music] means that new therapies are
tested in people whose body and immune
systems are already severely weakened
while their cancer is at the height of
its [music] strength.
So, perhaps it's time to give viruses a
chance earlier in the process,
when the cancer is only [music] getting
started and the body is not yet weakened
by more aggressive treatments.
To be crystal clear, virotherapy is not
[music] and won't be the cure to cancer.
Cancer is hundreds of different diseases
and the best therapy depends on the
type, location, [music] and how far it
has spread.
But in the best case, virotherapy could
be much less toxic
>> [music]
>> and as effective or better than chemo,
especially in combination with other
therapies.
Another weapon in our arsenal. [music]
So, what can we take away from Dr.
Halasz's story?
Her goal was to save her own life in the
face [music] of a terminal threat. It
was not without risk, but she succeeded.
And in the process, she hoped to inspire
more research on virotherapy [music] as
early options for patients to save other
lives like hers.
But she was also in a pretty unique
position to try this experiment. And
since she was doing it on herself, she
didn't [music] need to go through the
processes that would usually have slowed
it down or forbidden it.
In 2026, [music]
6 years after Beata's treatment, over a
dozen studies are underway to test
viruses [music]
as early-stage cancer therapies. And in
our book, this is hugely great news.
If you want to keep learning about
biology and science, we've got the
perfect poster series for you. Fill your
walls with knowledge every aspiring
scientist should have at a glance, from
our periodic table poster [music]
to our world map poster. Or dive into
complex topics like evolution and human
history, packed with fascinating details
you'll keep discovering over time. Every
poster is created in collaboration with
leading experts and meticulously
designed right here [music] at
Kurzgesagt. You can now build your own
educational poster wall and get 25% off,
exclusively available on the Kurzgesagt
shop.
You want to listen to the beautiful
soundtrack without my annoying voice?
Hmm, well, it's up to you. Just select
the audio track interlingua down here
and watch the video again as a music
video.